Howard A. Craig Papers
Howard A. Craig Papers
1918-1960
Craig, Howard A.
10 linear ft.
Papers of the U.S. Air Force officer. Collection includes correspondence (1938-1959); flight records (1937-1951); photographs; pilot's books; scrapbooks (1919-1959), and clippings.
149751
Biographical History
Howard A. "Pinky" Craig (1897-1977) was an American Air Force officer and pilot. He joined the Air Force during World War I and eventually rose to the rank of Lieutenant General. Over the course of his career he was a bomber pilot, commanded a fighter group in Tunisia, led the XII Air Support Command during the North Africa campaign, was on the General Staff of the War Department, headed the Alaskan Air Command, and served as commander of the National War College. His memoirs, Sunward I've Climbed: A Personal Narrative of Peace and War were published in 1975.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Howard A. Craig Papers consist of files containing correspondence, memorabilia, photographs, military material such as aerial maps and Army and Navy publications, and printed material. There are also eleven scrapbooks, some of which are formal commemorative albums and others are personal scrapbooks compiled by Craig.
Of particular interest are the extensive number of photographs from Craig's tenure in Alaska and during World War II, from the National War College, and from meetings of the Inter-American Defense Board (IADB) for which Craig served as president and on whose behalf he visited a number of countries in Latin American and South America. The IADB, formed in 1942, is an international committee of nationally appointed defense officials who collaborate on various aspects of defense; it also maintains the Inter-American Defense College (IADC). There are also two 16mm films featuring President Dwight D. Eisenhower on a visit to Adak, Alaska.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection was left in the arrangement and order in which it was received, and original folder titles were retained for the most part. Correspondence is therefore chronological rather than alphabetical.
Separated Material
Signed copy of Craig's memoirs, Sunward I've Climbed, transferred to Rare Books for cataloging, 12 Jan 2010.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Craig, Howard A.; Inter-American Defense Board.; National War College (U.S.); United States. -- Air Force.; United States. -- Air Force. -- Alaskan Air Command.; United States. -- Air Force -- History -- World War, 1939-1945.; United States. -- Air Force -- Officers.; United States. -- Air Force -- Officers -- Photographs.; United States. -- Army Air Forces.; United States. -- Army Air Forces. -- Bomb Group, 5th.; Aeronautics, Military -- United States.; Air pilots, Military.; United States -- History, Military -- 20th century.; 16mm (photographic film size); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Logs (records); Memorabilia.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Aeronautics.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- General files
  - Correspondence
    - Indexes to and/or lists of correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
      It is not known who created these lists. They may have come with the papers at the time of donation. Accuracy of the lists has not been determined.
    - General, 1938-1947; 9 folders (Box 1)
    - General, 1948-1952; 9 folders (Box 2)
    - General, 1953-1959; undated; 5 folders (Box 3)
    - Juan Peron, 1953 (Box 3)
    - "201 file", 1947-1952; military orders (Box 3)
  - National War College and Inter-American Defense Board, 1949-1955; orders (Box 3)
  - Orders and vouchers (Box 3)
  - Special orders (Box 3)
  - Individual flight records, 1937; 1943-1951; 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Flying time reports, 1921-1952 (gaps) (Box 4)
  - Speeches by HAC, 1952-1957; undated; most are National War College commencement addresses (Box 4)
  - Construction and transportation in Alaska, 1948; correspondence, Congressional Record items, etc. (Box 4)
  - Dept. of Defense Reserve Award to Solano County (California) Superintendent of Schools, 1957 (Box 4)
  - Itineraries, 1946; 1951,; 1953 (Box 4)
  - Eisenhower Visit to Adak, Alaska, craig_01; 16mm film; 1 reel, 200 feet (Oversize 1)
  - Eisenhower Visit to Adak, Alaska, dupe, craig_02; 16mm film; 1 reels, 200 feet (Oversize 1)
  - Letter, Marshall to Eisenhower, 7 May 1945 (Box 4)
  - Memorabilia, menus, calling cards, invitations (Box 4)
  - Memorabilia, photographs (Box 4)
  - Memorabilia, clippings (Box 4)
  - Proceedings, Board of Review, Airborne Operations, 1943-1944 (Box 5)
  - Inter-American Defense Board, 1952-1955; correspondence and related material (Box 5)
  - Report of Board of Officers on reorganization of War Department, 1945 (Box 5)
  - Algeria map (Box 5)
  - Japanese surrender, World War II (copy) (Oversize 3)
  - Pilot's books, no. 1-5, 1918-1932; 6 volumes (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - Alaska, 1946-1947; undated; Eisenhower, Fort Richardson, base hospital, Nakneck, Pt. Barrow, Ladd Field, inspections, etc. (Box 6)
    - Bad Godesberg, 1945 (Box 6)
    - Bohemian Grove, 1951 (Box 6)
    - Chile (Box 6)
    - Colombia, reception given by President Gustavo Rojas Pinilla (Box 6)
    - Dominican Republic (Box 6)
    - England, 1953; 1955,; undated (Box 6)
    - General Craig, 1944; 1947,; 1950-1956,; 1960,; undated; many are from meeting of Inter-American Defense Council; included are government and military personnel from Latin American and South American countries (Cuba, Peru, Argentina, Uruguay, etc.) (Box 6)
    - Guatemala (Box 6)
    - Haiti, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Inter-American Defense Board, 1953-1954; undated; includes color transparency of group shot from LIFE magazine (Box 6)
    - National War College, 1953-1955 (Box 6)
    - Rome, 1953 (Box 6)
    - Uruguay, 1952 (Box 6)
    - Venezuela, 1954 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1943-1957; many are of people being awarded medals (Box 6)
  - Published volume, Sunward I've Climbed, signed, Transferred to Rare Books for cataloging, 1/12/2010.
  - Reference material
    - Typescript manuscripts by others, speeches, articles, papers, addresses, etc.; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Published material, Air Force manuals, issues of LIFE magazine, The Eighth Army in Japan, The Navy Plan for National Security, Air Force yearbooks, etc.; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Published material, National War College material, The United States Strategic Bombing Survey (1945), Pacific Counterblow Interim Report, report on the Scientific Intelligence Center at Syracuse University Research Corp., assorted Army and Navy publications, Atlas de Cuba, aviation policy and strategy, etc.; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Newspaper and clippings, 1941-1947; 1956; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Newspaper and clippings, 1941-1946; includes issues of l'Algerienne (in French), Stars and Stripes; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - World War I air navigation maps (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 9)
    - Published articles about Craig, 1942-1957; 3 folders (Box 9)
- Scrapbooks
  - Alaska (I), presented to Craig by members of the Armed Forces Alaska (Oversize 5)
  - Alaska (II), mostly newspaper clippings; a few photographs and items of memorabilia (Oversize 2)
  - Argentina (I), 25 Nov 1953; souvenir book of photographs presented to Craig by the Argentine Ministry of Defense to commemorate his visit; handwritten title page (Oversize 6)
  - Argentina (II), 25 Nov 1953; souvenir book of photographs presented to Craig by the Argentine Ministry of Defense to commemorate his visit; printed title page, "Visita a la Argentina del Tenienio General Howard A. Craig" (Oversize 3)
  - Cuba, 1953; book of photographs and clippings, sent to Craig on the instructions of Major General Francisco Tabernilla Dolz, Chief of Staff of the Cuban Army (Oversize 6)
  - 5th Bombardment Wing, 1959; 40th anniversary commemorative book, signed and inscribed to Craig by Lucion N. Powell, Commander (Oversize 7)
  - National War College graduation, Jun 1955; during Craig's tenure as commandant of NWC (Oversize 7)
  - "A souvenir from the Uruguayan Navy", 20-23 Nov 1953; presented to Craig while he was president of Inter-American Defense Board; mostly photographs (Box 10)
  - [Miscellaneous I], 1919-1946; quote from Andrew Jackson pasted inside front cover; correspondence, military orders, clippings, photographs; includes reproduction of 1898 photograph of Signal Corps Officers in Jacksonville, Florida (Box 10)
  - [Miscellaneous II], 1939-1940; appears to have been compiled during Craig family's time in Florida; clippings from Miami and Tampa newspapers, photographs, postcards, memorabilia, etc. (Oversize 7)
  - [Miscellaneous III], 1942-1947; bulk relates to World War II, with a few later items; bulk is newspaper clippings, a few photographs and other items (Oversize 4)